On the 6th of January, 1066,
Harold Godwinson, the head of England's
most powerful noble family, was crowned
at Westminster Abbey.
King Harold II was the first English
ruler ever to be crowned at Westminster.
His coronation was unusual in other
ways.
It took place only one day after the
death of King Edward the Confessor.
It also marked the beginning of one of
the shortest reigns in English royal
history, one that ended 9 months later
at the Battle of Hastings.
Why was Harold in such a rush to be
crowned king in January 1066, and on
what basis did he claim the throne in
the first place?
This is the story of Harold Godwinson
and the Norman Conquest of England.
The man known to history as Harold
Godwinson, or King Harold II of England,
is understood to have been born either
in the year 1022
or 1023.
This was most likely in the Wessex
region of Southern England, perhaps at
Winchester, but this is conjectural and
there is no definitive document or
account stating where and when he was
born.
Harold's father, unsurprisingly given
Harold's surname, Godwinson, was Godwin
of Wessex.
Godwin's father was quite possibly
Wulfnoth Cild, a thane or local lord of
Sussex in southern England.
Wulfnoth was not a powerful national
figure, but he did carve out a position
of importance in the English Channel in
the early 11th century by controlling a
small fleet here that engaged regularly
in piracy.
Although he was an Anglo-Saxon lord,
Godwin rose in the years before Harold
was born through service to King Cnut, a
Danish king of England.
Godwin became Earl of Wessex around four
or five years before Harold was born.
Over time, he rose to become the most
powerful lord in the kingdom of England,
a development which would pave the way
for Harold to become king himself one
day.
Godwin married Gytha Thorkelsdóttir.
She was a Danish noblewoman from an
esteemed family.
Her brother was Ulf Thorgilsson, a
Danish earl who married Estrid
Svendsdatter, a sister of Cnut the
Great, the man who eventually rose to
become king of England, Denmark, and
Norway.
Thus, Harold, who was half Anglo-Saxon
and half Danish, rose in large part
because of his father's advantageous
marriage into the Danish nobility.
Gytha and Godwin had numerous other
children.
Amongst these were three different sons
and a daughter who would all play
prominent parts in Harold's life and
career.
Three of his brothers, Sweyn, Tostig,
and Gyrth, would all violently oppose
him at different times, though Gyrth
would ultimately die fighting alongside
his brother at Hastings in 1066.
Harold's sister, Edith, would marry
Edward the Confessor and was queen
consort of England for 21 years before
Harold secured the throne in January
1066.
The kingdom that Harold was born into
was at the center of an oddly
cosmopolitan world.
For centuries in the early Middle Ages,
large parts of Europe had very little
contact with places just a few hundred
kilometers away.
The various Anglo-Saxon kingdoms of 7th
century England, for instance, did not
have extensive connections with the
kingdom of the Franks in France or the
Visigothic kingdom in Spain.
That all changed with the rise of the
Norse people in the late 8th century and
their conquest and settlement of lands
as disparate as Iceland, Ireland,
Orkney, northern England, Normandy in
France, and large parts of Eastern
Europe.
A new interconnected Europe was created,
one in which the North Sea and the
English Channel became highways rather
than obstacles.
The arrival of the Danes also spurred on
the unification of England in the late
9th and early 10th centuries.
These new webs of politics and genealogy
all around northern Europe meant that
Danes and Norwegians were heavily
involved in England during Harold's
time.
In 1013,
Sweyn Forkbeard, the king of Denmark and
Norway, had conquered [music] England.
Although the House of Wessex was briefly
reestablished in 1014, in 1016, King
Cnut, a Dane, had seized the English
throne. He would rule down to his death
in 1035,
eventually becoming the ruler of a North
Sea Empire that covered England,
Denmark, and Norway.
This meant that England was a kingdom
split between old Anglo-Saxon families
and more recent Danish noble lines.
These families had intermarried with
Danes and Northmen elsewhere in places
like Ireland and Normandy in northern
France.
All of these disparate ties and
interconnected politics would have a
bearing over Harold's life and his brief
reign as King of England.
Compared with English lords and rulers
of the early Middle Ages, there are
quite a lot of sources available for
studying the life of Harold Godwinson.
For instance, the Anglo-Saxon Chronicle,
a large analytic history that covers
hundreds of years of England's medieval
history and which was added to over
time, provides accounts of events in the
11th century.
Numerous histories of the era were
written by church scholars during the
late 11th and 12th centuries, notably
William of Malmesbury and William of
Poitiers.
Harold is one of the central figures of
the famous Bayeux Tapestry depicting the
events leading up to, during, and
following the Norman Conquest of
England, a visual source that sheds
great light on his life and role in
these events.
However, all of these sources are biased
and they usually present a resoundingly
negative picture of Harold.
Nearly all of the information that has
come down to us was written from the
perspective of the Normans, who viewed
Harold as having tried to seize the
crown that rightfully belonged to
William of Normandy.
Hence, Harold's actions were not
presented in an objective manner.
Even the Domesday Book, a record of land
ownership across England produced 20
years after Harold's time, contains a
fundamental bias against Godwinson as
the compilers of it tried to
fundamentally disavow the idea that he
had ever ruled as King of England,
however brief his reign might have been.
There, he was referred to as Haraldus
Comes,
Count Harold, though the sheer number of
references to his former landholdings
made it evident that he had not been any
normal lord.
This sustained hostility to Harold in
the written record needs to be kept in
mind while evaluating his life and
reign.
The details of Harold's early life on a
personal level are limited.
This is typical of the time.
Chroniclers weren't interested in
describing the childhood education of
kings or nobles, and these could often
be limited in any event in the 11th
century.
For instance, William the Conqueror was
famously illiterate.
While we know virtually nothing about
Harold's childhood, it is utterly clear
that his fortunes were dictated by his
father's actions and how the family was
promoted to immense power.
King Cnut died in 1035.
A power struggle followed, in which
Godwin supported the claim of
Harthacnut, a son of Cnut.
When he finally secured the throne in
1040, it meant that Godwin and his
family were promoted to become one of
the most powerful families in England.
This was then compounded when Harold's
sister, Edith, married King Edward the
Confessor, the ruler of England from
1042 onwards.
Godwin paved the way for Edward, who had
been living in exile in Normandy in
northern France, to return to England
and secure the throne in 1042.
Pursuant from these developments, Edith
became queen consort of England,
Harold's older brother, Sweyn, became
Earl of the Southwest Midlands in 1043,
his younger brother, Tostig, became Earl
of Northumbria in 1055,
and two of his other brothers, Leofwine
and Gyrth, would each acquire earldoms
in due course.
Godwin had clearly reached the point
where he was the most powerful lord of
the realm as father-in-law of King
Edward the Confessor.
Not only did he manage to form a
marriage alliance with Edward by
marrying his daughter to him, he became
the real power behind the throne in
England.
While Edward was viewed as an extremely
pious and well-intentioned ruler, he was
ultimately dominated by Godwin
throughout his reign.
This was the backdrop against which
Harold would rise in the kingdom's
politics and eventually briefly become
king of England in 1066.
Harold was promoted along with his
brothers.
Around 1045, he was made Earl of East
Anglia with lands stretching across what
is now East Anglia, Essex,
Cambridgeshire, and Huntingdonshire.
This followed the banishing of the
previous Earl of East Anglia, a Dane
named Osgod Clapa,
who had been a prominent figure during
the reigns of several kings going back
to the time of King Cnut, and who had
served as staller, the master of the
royal stables.
He was forced out under mysterious
circumstances around 1045 and sent into
exile where he conspired against King
Edward.
Harold, at only around 23 years of age,
took his position as the most powerful
lord in East Anglia.
As well as forming strong ties from
early in his 20s with the foremost
political and ecclesiastical figures in
East Anglia, Harold took as his
concubine at this time a woman named
Edith Swan-neck or Swan's Hals.
She came from a very prominent family
and may have been a granddaughter of
Æthelred the Unready, the king of
England between 978 and the civil wars
of the mid-1010s.
Her father was Thorkell the Tall, a
prominent Danish lord in England in
earlier times.
They would have five children together.
They do not appear to have ever married,
though concubine relationships of this
kind were common in the 10th and 11th
centuries.
More broadly, the relationship reflected
Harold's attempts to form close ties to
some of the most powerful Danish
aristocratic lineages in England.
For instance, he also formed an alliance
with Stigand, the Bishop of Elmham, a
cleric of mixed Anglo-Saxon and Danish
ancestry.
Edith brought Harold additional land and
power, too. She had inherited extensive
lands in Eastern England and was known
euphemistically as the rich on account
of her inheritance.
While Harold had already risen to become
a powerful lord in East Anglia and
nationally by the mid-1040s,
his position was augmented further from
1046 onwards.
This came about owing to internal family
disputes and the sheer lack of political
judgment displayed by his older brother,
Sweyn.
Had the latter been willing to bide his
time and build his power, he could have
become the most powerful noble of the
realm in future years once his father
had passed away.
Instead, he was overly anxious to
acquire a great position within
England's affairs and committed a series
of highly inflammatory acts in his
attempt to expand his influence.
This included kidnapping the abbess of
the powerful convent of Leominster.
A year later, after committing several
other indiscretions, he was banished
from England and fled into exile in the
low countries before finally heading to
Denmark.
His extensive earldom was then divided
up between Harold, a Danish lord, and a
cousin of the House of Godwin named
Beorn Estrithson, and a lord from
Normandy, Richard of Mortain.
Sweyn returned to England before too
long to try to reclaim his position and
ended up murdering Beorn, a crime which
led to him being banished yet again.
Although he miraculously managed to
acquire a second pardon in 1050 and was
allowed to return home once again, Sweyn
never reacquired his father's favor.
Henceforth, Godwin placed his hopes for
the future on Harold and viewed him as
the son who would succeed him
politically as the preeminent aristocrat
in England.
Godwin's growing reliance on Harold as a
stable son who could support the
family's political ambitions became
doubly necessary around 1050.
Despite the marriage of Edward to
Harold's sister, King Edward's
relationship with Godwin had cooled and
he was in danger of losing his status as
the power behind the throne.
The main point of contention was over
the appointment of a new Archbishop of
Canterbury, the premier ecclesiastical
office in England.
Godwin and Harold, along with a large
proportion of the monks of the Abbey of
Canterbury, favored the candidacy of
Æthelric, a kinsman of Godwin's and also
a monk of the local Abbey.
The king instead favored the appointment
of Robert of Jumièges, the Bishop of
London since 1044.
Edward had spent his youth in Normandy
and Robert was a Norman who he had known
for over a decade before he returned to
England to become king.
Robert was hugely opposed to the power
of Godwin and his family, viewing the
Earl, Harold, Queen Edith, and the rest
of the family as having acquired a near
monopoly on power across England.
In the midst of the dispute over the
succession to the Archbishopric in 1051,
Eustace, Count of Boulogne, a French
lord who was married to King Edward's
sister, arrived at southern England and
ended up in an armed altercation with
Godwin's retainers near Dover.
When Godwin was ordered by the king to
inflict punishment on the local
burgesses for their actions, he refused,
leading Edward to banish Godwin and the
rest of the family.
While his father and most of his family
left England for Flanders in the Low
Countries, Harold and his brother,
Leofwine, headed to Ireland, where he
formed an alliance with Diarmait mac
Máel na mBó, the King of Leinster.
Sweyn, the brother who had created so
much unrest over the past years, headed
off on pilgrimage to Jerusalem.
He died on the return trip.
Thus, as 1051 came to an end, it
appeared that the House of Godwin's
fortunes were at a low ebb and that
Harold and his father and siblings could
well live out their days in exile.
Even Harold's sister, Edith, the Queen
of England, had been temporarily forced
into a convent in England by her
husband.
The temporary fall of Earl Godwin and
his family was very He short-lived.
Godwin and his sons in the Low
Countries, with the support of his
wife's Danish relatives, organized
support from around the North Sea world,
while Harold acquired aid from Ireland.
They then converged on England in 1052.
There, their English allies rose in
support of them as well.
It was clear immediately to King Edward
that he could not resist Godwin and his
family.
He relented and restored Godwin, Harold,
and his brothers to their earldoms.
Edith was released from her confinement
and resumed her position as queen.
Edward would never again try to
challenge the preeminent position of the
House of Godwin within England.
Only a year later, Harold was the head
of that house.
His father died on the 15th of April,
1053, possibly from a stroke.
With this, Harold, at 30 or 31 years of
age, succeeded as Earl of Wessex and
became the most powerful lord of the
realm.
Moreover, this occurred just as the
family was reaching the peak of its
power.
With Edward's resistance to their
influence broken in 1052, Harold and his
family continued to amass unparalleled
power, land, and wealth in the
mid-to-late 1050s.
By the end of the decade, in addition to
holding earldoms that stretched across
southern and eastern England, the family
had also acquired lands in Mercia, in
the Midlands, and the west, and even
north into Yorkshire.
Their estates generated an annual income
of 8,500
lbs, an enormous sum in the 11th
century.
By comparison, King Edward's own estates
generated 2,500
lbs.
Edward the Confessor was King of
England, but power and wealth lay in the
hands of Harold Godwinson and his family
members.
Harold's position as England's
preeminent noble translated into
becoming a major patron of the church in
East Anglia, Wessex, and beyond.
Amongst the religious houses that he
provided funding and support for was
Peterborough Abbey.
The abbot there, Leofric, would later
fight alongside him at the Battle of
Hastings in 1066.
Harold also developed ties to Ely Abbey
and provided the house with relics as a
token of his aristocratic patronage.
However, the religious house that he
gave the greatest support to was Waltham
Holy Cross Abbey in Essex.
Here, he organized the construction of a
new church for the religious community
and a large stone cross there.
His patronage was based around a
distinct cult of the cross that existed
in the Anglo-Scandinavian North Sea
world in the 10th and 11th centuries,
one which saw life-size stone crosses
erected within many church grounds and
abbeys.
He also patronized the creation of a
series of beautiful manuscripts that
filled Waltham's library.
While his own literacy levels are
unclear, Harold evidently had an
interest in manuscripts which were as
much picture books as written texts
during the High Middle Ages.
It is known, for instance, that he owned
an elaborate book on the subject of
falconry.
He need not have been literate to
appreciate this.
The text could have been read to him.
Harold's patronage of Waltham involved
providing the institution with saints'
relics.
These included an alleged piece of St.
Peter's chain and a piece of his beard.
Relics of this kind were common
throughout medieval Europe.
It was not unheard of for there to be
five or six examples of the same saint's
hands at various monasteries, churches,
convents, and cathedrals across the
continent.
What was unusual at Waltham
is that some of these relics had been
brought directly to the religious house
by its lay patron.
Harold went on pilgrimage to Rome around
the year 1057 or 1058.
This was very typical of the era.
There was a surge in religious sentiment
across Europe in the 11th century,
fueled by the turn of the millennium
when concerns about the potential end of
days around the year 1000 receded, and a
new religious fervor emerged,
culminating in the Crusades in Iberia,
northern Europe, and the Levant.
This resulted in many rulers making the
pilgrimage to Rome,
notably King Macbeth of Scotland, the
king on whose rule William Shakespeare's
play was loosely based.
Macbeth had made his pilgrimage to Rome
seven or eight years before Harold.
In addition to visiting the standard
pilgrimage sites within and around the
Eternal City, Harold most likely
petitioned for an audience with the Pope
in relation to disputes that had arisen
over ecclesiastical and secular lands in
southern England following the
appointment of the powerful Stigand as
Robert of Jumièges' successor as
Archbishop of Canterbury.
This could have been with any one of
three different Popes,
Victor II, Stephen IX, or Nicholas II,
as there was a rapid turnover of heads
of the Roman Catholic Church between
1057 and 1059.
What the outcome was, if he did petition
against Stigand, is unclear.
The cleric remained as Archbishop of
Canterbury for the remainder of Harold's
lifetime.
Harold's pilgrimage to Rome was part of
a much wider expedition around Europe
between 1056 and 1058.
It is concretely known that he traveled
to Flanders in what is now Belgium in
the autumn of 1056.
He traveled onwards to Germany
afterwards, possibly on his way to Rome,
though this is not known for certain.
Historians of Harold's reign and 11th
century England tend to agree that his
continental adventure was connected with
the presence of Edward the Exile in
Central Europe at that time.
This Edward was a son of Edmund
Ironside, who was briefly King of
England for seven months in 1016 before
Cnut claimed the throne.
Edward was an infant upon Cnut's
succession, and the new Danish king sent
him England to prevent him becoming a
source of conspiracy against his rule in
future years.
Edward's subsequent life trajectory is
debated. He was first in Scandinavia,
and then may have spent time in the
Kievan Rus in Eastern Europe before
ending up in Hungary for many years.
News of his presence there had reached
England, and Harold was quite possibly
on the continent in 1056 to facilitate
Edward's return to England to become the
acknowledged heir to Edward the
Confessor.
In doing so, he would have hoped to gain
influence over the future king and
become the power behind the throne in a
subsequent reign. The plan did not
succeed.
While Edward the Exile did return to
England early in 1057, he died within
days of meeting with the king and having
his status as the new heir recognized.
The timing of Harold's travel to Europe
and Edward's return to England seems far
too coincidental for him not to have
played a role in Edward's arrival back
in Britain.
This was possibly not Harold's only
foray to the continent.
In 1064, he is also believed to have
made the short trip over the English
Channel to Normandy to visit the court
of Duke William of Normandy.
This was highly significant.
Harold's brother-in-law, King Edward,
did not have an heir.
Historians have never been able to agree
on whether Edward's lack of an heir was
because his extreme religious piety,
which earned him the sobriquet the
Confessor, meant that he remained
celibate or simply because he and Edith
were unable to have children.
Whatever the cause of it, we know that
Edward did not have an heir, and there
was no obvious relative to succeed him
after the death of Edward the Exile
following his return to England years
earlier.
The story spread by the Normans after
the Norman Conquest was that Edward
preempted a succession crisis by
acknowledging William of Normandy as his
designated heir as early as 1051.
By 1064,
it was clear that Edward would never
produce an heir.
Thus, a number of records state that
Harold was sent to Normandy in 1064 to
confirm to William that he was to
succeed Edward when he died.
The only issue is that the sources that
make these claims were produced by
Norman writers in the years after the
Norman Conquest of 1066.
Therefore, it is possible that Harold
made no such visit to the Norman court
at Rouen, Normandy in 1064, and that
this was later invented to bolster
William of Normandy's claim to the
English throne.
Harold had been the head of the House of
Godwin since his father's death in 1053.
Additionally, his older brother, Sweyn,
who had been the troublesome member of
the family, had died the previous year.
On the face of it, this had reduced the
problem of fractious members of the
family, but in 1065,
brother, Tostig, the Earl of Northumbria
since 1055,
and the family's most important figure
in the north of England, ended up mired
in controversy.
The local lords there rebelled against
him and tried to install Morcar, a
grandson of an old Mercian Earl named
Leofric, as the new ruler of the north.
Their argument was that Tostig was
acting above his station and was trying
to build up a base of support in the
north to challenge both Harold and the
king.
Tostig was driven out by these lords and
went into exile.
Harold did not try to save his brother.
Instead, aware that Edward was ill and
that a contested succession was pending,
he allied with the northern lords and
married a prominent Mercian noblewoman
named Ealdgyth.
By the time the lords of the north
rebelled against Tostig's influence
there and moved to expel him, the king's
health was declining.
After Harold's brother went into exile
and as he moved to marry Ealdgyth, it
became evident that Edward was going to
die.
This was clear when Westminster Abbey
was consecrated on the 29th of December
1065.
There had been a Benedictine Abbey here
since the 10th century, but Edward had
made it part of his life's work to have
a great new Abbey built at the site
outside London.
Thus, when it was announced that he
would not be able to attend the
consecration of the Abbey that he had
spent so much of his reign working on,
no one was in any doubt that something
was gravely wrong with him.
He died a week later.
The usual date given for his death is
the 5th of January 1066, though it may
have been on the night of the 4th.
The claim subsequently went out around
the country that Edward had named Harold
as his successor on his deathbed.
Then, with unseemly haste, Edward was
buried on the 6th of January, and Harold
was crowned the very same day at
Westminster Abbey, becoming the first
king to have his coronation at the new
Abbey.
The suspicion has always been that
Harold moved to hold his coronation as
quickly as he did because he knew his
claim to the throne was weak, and he
wanted to cement it as quickly as
possible.
In this manner, Harold Godwinson became
King Harold II of England, and the
282-day-long
dynastic reign of the House of Godwin
commenced.
The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle remarked in an
understated way about Harold's time as
king that
"He met little quiet in it as long as he
ruled the realm."
This was an understatement, to say the
least.
Harold's accession was challenged by two
other men.
One of these was William of Normandy,
whom Edward had potentially earmarked as
his designated heir, and whom several
admittedly biased Norman chroniclers
would later claim that Harold had gone
to Normandy to acknowledge as the heir
in 1064.
A second claimant emerged from across
the North Sea, and he was the rival that
Harold would have to see off a challenge
from first.
His name was Harald Hardrada.
Harald was the son of a local king in
Norway, Sigurd Syr.
As a teenager, he fled from Scandinavia
after a power struggle and spent the
entirety of the 1030s and early 1040s as
a mercenary in the Kievan Rus' in
Eastern Europe and within the Byzantine
Empire.
He eventually returned to his homeland
in Scandinavia and claimed the crown of
Norway.
When Edward died in January 1066,
>> [music]
>> Tostig, Harold's brother, who had
recently been ousted from his position
of power in the north of England,
encouraged him to try to claim the
English throne.
In early September, his plans were
advanced enough that he sailed across
the North Sea and met up with Tostig's
forces in northern England.
Harold responded energetically and
marched north to confront his rival and
his brother.
They met on the field of battle at
Stamford Bridge in Yorkshire on the 25th
of September.
This was a large battle by 11th century
English standards involving upwards of
20,000 men in all.
The Norse chronicles later claimed that
Harold sent a messenger to Tostig
offering to pardon him and grant him an
earldom again if he withdrew his support
for Hardrada.
His brother refused and in the resulting
clash, Tostig was killed along with
Hardrada as Harold managed to defeat his
first challenger.
Under normal circumstances, the Battle
of Stamford Bridge would have been a
great feat of arms for an English king
that secured the throne.
Harold, though, was entirely unlucky to
face two different invasions of England
at exactly the same time.
Three days after Harold defeated
Hardrada and Tostig's combined forces at
Stamford Bridge in the north,
William of Normandy landed with his own
army at Pevensey in Sussex on the
southern coast of England.
He was now much closer to London than
Harold was.
News reached Godwinson of William's
invasion of England on the 3rd of
October, 1066.
As a result, Harold had to march south
with his army at speed without fully
recovering from the Battle of Stamford
Bridge.
This was a distance of nearly 250 miles
traversed in 12 days, or approximately
20 miles per day.
For an army in the 11th century, that
was an extremely swift pace carrying
heavy weaponry and armor and the march
following so soon after a forced march
northwards and a battle against
Hardrada's army tired out Harold's men
even further.
At the end of the rapid southward
journey,
his forces had little time to rest
before confronting William's Norman host
near Hastings in Sussex in the south of
England on the 14th of October, 1066.
Although it should be noted that more
recently a claim has been made by
academic Professor Tom Licence that
Harold's forces actually arrived by sea
and that his forces arrived fresh and
rested.
A substantial departure from the largely
accepted version of events.
Modern estimates suggest both armies
most likely ranged between about 6,000
and 9,000 men.
The clash would decide the fate of
England and Harold Godwinson.
A unique account of the Battle of
Hastings survives from the Bayeux
Tapestry, the rich visual depiction of
the events leading up to and throughout
the Norman Conquest of England.
At dawn on the morning of the battle,
Harold prepared his forces on an
elevated ridge where Battle Abbey stands
today, a religious establishment later
built by the Normans to commemorate the
scene of their most famous victory.
Here, Harold's forces formed a shield
wall that probably stretched a half a
kilometer long and which, in tandem with
their elevated position, was designed to
stop any Norman cavalry charge.
While this line of infantry was the core
of Harold's army, the Normans relied to
a great extent on their cavalry, the
elite shock troops of Europe during the
High Middle Ages.
While both sides had archers available,
an issue for Harold's forces, which
quite possibly contributed to his
defeat, was a lack of arrows.
The Anglo-Danish army had simply
expended a large number of arrows at
Stamford Bridge and didn't have time to
replenish their stores before clashing
with the Normans at Hastings.
What followed was a battle in which the
Normans were the aggressor, constantly
launching charges to try to break the
Anglo-Danish lines.
The fighting went on all day, according
to accounts, only finally concluding as
the light was fading over the
battlefield.
The cause of the eventual victory was
the killing of Harold.
There are differing accounts. One
suggests that he was isolated by the
Normans and killed by several of
William's followers.
Another describes an arrow striking him
in the eye underneath the rim of his
helmet. A version of events which
corresponds with the Bayeux Tapestry.
As he fell, the resolve of his followers
collapsed and the Normans won the field.
Two of Harold's younger brothers, Gyrth
and Leofwine, both fell fighting as well
at Hastings.
It is not entirely certain what happened
to Harold's body after the Battle of
Hastings.
An account written from a Norman
perspective claimed that he was buried
near the battlefield.
It is more probable though that his
remains were taken to Waltham Holy Cross
Abbey and laid to rest at the religious
site that he had patronized so greatly
in life.
A tradition even holds that his first
wife or concubine, Edith, showed up to
Hastings after the fighting and
organized the transport of his body to
Waltham.
While the arrival of his recently
spurned concubine to oversee the
retrieval of his body from the
battlefield is possibly too colorful a
story to be believed, it is nonetheless
almost certainly the case that Harold's
body was taken to Waltham and laid to
rest there.
His body was moved three times over the
next 110 years as the site was
redeveloped and despite his status as
the ruler who had opposed the Norman
conquerors, a local cult seems to have
developed at Waltham around his remains
in the late 11th and 12th centuries, a
sign of the residual support for the
House of Godwin and the old Anglo-Saxon
aristocracy for decades after the Norman
Conquest.
His remains were demoted as a scene of
residual royal worship in 1177
when King Henry II reformed Waltham
Abbey and refounded it as an Augustinian
Priory of the Canons Regular as part of
his efforts to reform the church and
religious houses throughout England.
An alternative legend developed not long
after Harold's death which claimed that
he had not actually died at all at the
Battle of Hastings.
This account is found in the Vita Harold
or Life of Harold, an anonymous Latin
text which was copied out by a scribe at
Waltham around the year 1205
though the text is based on an early
tradition.
This claimed that Harold was wounded at
Hastings but did not die.
Instead, his supporters spirited him
away to Winchester, the ancestral
capital of the kings of the House of
Wessex.
He spent two years in secret there
recovering from the injuries he had
sustained in the battle.
Then, with the Normans in control of
England, he made his escape from the
kingdom he had once briefly ruled.
According to the Vita, he spent several
years traveling around as a pilgrim on
the continent in Germany and adjoining
lands.
Eventually, he returned to England and
went by the name of Christian.
There, he spent a 10-year long period
living as a hermit near Dover in a cave
before traversing the country to the
town of Chester.
It was here that he spent the last part
of his life, finally admitting to a
confessor before his death that he was
old King Harold II and had survived his
famous showdown with William the
Conqueror at Hastings.
The Vita Harold I provides a colorful
alternative ending to the Battle of
Hastings, but there is no reason to
believe that anything written in it was
anything other than fantasy.
Of course, Harold's death at Hastings
did not bring the Norman Conquest of
England to an end.
Harold's cause had many supporters
still, and there were other Anglo-Saxon
and Danish lords of England who were
viewed as more favorable candidates to
become King of England rather than
allowing a foreign interloper from
France to seize the throne through brute
force.
For instance, in the immediate aftermath
of the defeat at Hastings, Edgar
Atheling, a young grandson of King
Edmund Ironside, who had briefly ruled
England half a century earlier in 1016,
and a son of Edward the Exile, was
elected as King of the English by a
Witten Council, albeit he submitted to
William within weeks when the new king
reached London.
The fighting in parts of England
continued for many years.
William and his Norman companions
unleashed a devastating campaign of
violence and scorched earth across
England and the borderlands with Wales
in order to secure their control over
the country, and by the start of the
1070s, they were more firmly in control
of England.
The same Domesday Book, which tried to
suggest that Harold was never anything
greater than an earl, provides a window
into how dramatic the scale of the
change in landholding across England was
by the mid-1080s.
William didn't just defeat Harold and
conquer the country.
He introduced an entirely new ruling
class, one which spoke a different
language, governed using different laws
and systems, and which had a
fundamentally different culture.
England's language, law, customs, and
political system would not be what they
are today if William had not defeated
Harold at Hastings.
Moreover, because England's systems and
culture were exported to almost every
corner of the world at the height of
Britain's empire in the 18th and 19th
centuries, the Battle of Hastings had an
unusually large bearing on the course of
world history.
Not everyone was willing to accept the
new dispensation.
Several of Harold's sons continued their
opposition to William and the Normans in
the years that followed.
At first, they withdrew to the West
Country and used this as a base from
which they coordinated their movements
against the invaders.
Later, as William's control over England
grew, they fled from the country
altogether and settled in Ireland.
From Dublin, Harold's son Godwin
obtained the patronage of Diarmait, the
King of Leinster and a claimant to the
high kingship of Ireland.
From there, we are led to believe from
numerous Irish and Anglo-Norman
chronicles that they launched several
major raids against England in the late
1060s, one involving dozens of ships
that sailed up the Severn Estuary
towards Bristol.
Ultimately, these attacks were
unsuccessful.
Harold's many children eventually ended
up dispersing far and wide across
Europe, marrying into royal and noble
households in Scandinavia and even as
far away as Ruthenia, around modern-day
Lithuania and Belarus.
While most medieval accounts of Harold,
barring legendary ones like that found
in the Vita Haroldi, were uniform in
trying to present an image of an
illegitimate king who was defeated and
killed by the rightful successor to the
throne, popular views of Harold changed
in the 19th century.
For instance, in 1876,
Alfred, Lord Tennyson, produced a play
entitled Harold.
It departed from the stereotypical
depiction of Harold and instead
portrayed him as a heroic, though
ultimately doomed, ruler of England.
28 years earlier, in 1848, Edward
Bulwer-Lytton had published Harold, the
Last of the Saxon Kings, a similarly
nuanced work of historical fiction in
which Harold appears as an ultimately
righteous ruler whose morality is
compromised by the challenges to his
rule.
These literary works were augmented by
E. A. Freeman's History of the Norman
Conquest of England, published as a
multi-volume study in the 1870s.
Here, Harold was also depicted as a
misunderstood hero of England's medieval
history.
These works were the product of the deep
sense of romantic nationalism that
pervaded Europe in the middle of the
19th century.
They show how the life story of a ruler
like Harold could be bent from being a
piece of negative propaganda as
presented by the Normans in the High
Middle Ages to become an entirely new
piece of mythology suited to the
politics of the 19th century.
History is filled with stories of
winners and losers, those who claimed
power and those who lost it.
William the Conqueror is amongst the
most famous victors in human history. A
man who conquered a kingdom, changed its
language, laws, and culture, and in
doing so, altered the fabric of world
history.
Harold Godwinson is the counterpoint to
William.
Where William conquered, Harold lost his
life and kingdom in 1066.
His story is one of defeat.
At least, that is what it looks like
when there is nothing but a narrow focus
on the events of October 1066, and when
the overwhelmingly hostile source
material is accepted at face value.
There was more to Harold Godwinson than
this, though.
He came from the most powerful noble
family in 11th century England and had
an important career for more than 20
years before he ever became king.
This included his rise to dominate the
East Anglia region politically and
culturally and then his emergence as a
noble in the 1050s who was more powerful
than King Edward the Confessor.
His extended career allowed him to build
up support for his claim to the throne
and when Edward died in January 1066,
Harold became the first monarch to be
crowned at Westminster Abbey a day
later.
Had Harold faced a single challenger, he
might well have been able to secure the
throne and establish a secure dynasty.
In the end, the House of Godwin only
lasted 9 and 1/2 months.
While Harold defeated Harald Hardrada at
the Battle of Stamford Bridge in
September, his supposedly depleted and
worn out forces could not repeat the
victory at the Battle of Hastings 3
weeks later.
Harold's reign was consequently one of
the shortest in English royal history.
But Harold was not a trivial individual.
He was unlucky more so than incompetent.
What do you think of Harold Godwinson?
Was he the legitimate king of England
who was overthrown by an upstart
conqueror from France or was Harold the
real upstart who tried to claim the
throne that Edward had promised to
[music] William of Normandy years
earlier?
Please, let us know in the comment
section.
And in the meantime, thank you very much
for watching.
>> Mhm.